Morgan Russell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Microfilm of the Morgan Russell papers
1891-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Morgan Russell
6.8 linear feet on 19 microfilm reels
The Morgan Russell papers, 1891-1977, present a good overview of Russell's career as a painter and sculptor, with an emphasis on his development of the color theory movement, Synchromism. The papers include correspondence, biographical material, transcripts of lectures given by Russell, illustrated notebooks and sketches, printed material and photographs.
Biographical Note
Painter and sculptor Morgan Russell was born in New York City. He studied at the Art Students League and the New York School of Art with James Earle Fraser, Andrew Dasburg and Robert Henri from 1906 to 1907, before settling in Paris in 1909 where he remained for almost forty years. After meeting Stanton Macdonald-Wright in 1911, he became interested in Synchromism and studied with Canadian color theorist Ernest Tudor-Hart. In 1913 Russell produced the first abstract Synchromies and in 1917 developed a series of Synchromies entitled EIDOS. He visited California in the early 1930s, teaching at the Chouinard School of Art in Los Angeles from 1931-1932, in addition to lecturing at museums in Los Angeles and San Francisco. Russell left France permanently in 1946 and died in Pennsylvania in 1953.
Scope and Content Note
The Morgan Russell papers present a good overview of Russell's career as a painter and sculptor, with an emphasis on his development of the color theory movement, Synchromism. The papers include correspondence with many prominent individuals who played a role in Russell's artistic development; biographical material primarily documenting his activities in Europe; transcripts of lectures given by Russell; illustrated notebooks and sketches documenting his interest in, and development of, color theory, music and Synchromism; printed material such as exhibition announcements, catalogs and clippings; and photographs of Russell, his wife, friends and artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series according to record type and reflecting the lender's arrangement. With the exception of Series 1: Correspondence, all series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1909-1964 (Reels 4524-4527)
Series 2: Biographical Material, 1925-1941 (Reel 4527)
Series 3: Business Records, 1911-1946 (Reel 4527)
Series 4: Writings, 1931-1953 (Reel 4527)
Series 5: Unbound Notes and Sketches, 1891-1977 (Reels 4528-4538)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1908-1963 (Reels 4539-4541)
Series 7: Photographs, 1908-1948 (Reel 4542)
Appendix: Miscellaneous Correspondents/Postcards from Series 1: Correspondence
Alsthom: April 18, 1944
Altenburg, Alexandre: undated letters (5), October 21, 1925, May 3, 29, 1926, July 3, 9, 1926, October 14, 20, 1927, December 13, 1927, July 12, 1928, September 11, 1928*, October 8, 1928, November 3, 1928, November 17, 1929, November 27, 1929, December 3, 1929, May 28, 1930, June 26, 1929, 1930*, September 7, 1930, October 9, 1930, May 27, 1931, May 2, 1936, September 16, 1937, November 2, 1939, April 24, 1940
Altenburg, Alexandre and Otto: January 21, 1940
Alvarez, Mabel (letters to Russell from Alvarez): undated letters (6), September 17, 1913*, July 16, 1932, May 13, 1933, October 20, 1933, December 8, 1933, August 17, 1934, October 31, 1934, July 14, 1935, September 17, 1935, October 4, 1935, December 3, 1935, January 9, 1936, March 9, 1936, April 21, 1936, October 3, 1936, August 18, 1936, November 6, 1936, January 29, 1937, April 13, 1937?, July 5, 1937, August 5, 1937, September 22, 1937, November 16, 1937, January 22, 1938, February 23, 1938, May 23, 1938, September 25, 1938, October 8, 1938, November 16, 1938, January 29, 1939, April 16, 1939, May 6, 1939, July 5, 1939* August 24, 1939, November 9, 1939, February 1, 1940, March 7, 1940, July 20,1940, January 16, 1945, July 4, 1945, October 28, 1945
Alvarez, Mabel (letters to Alvarez from Russell): November 15, 1934, February 21, 1935, June 18, 1935, July 31, 1935, October 10, 26, 1935, December 15, 1935, March 26, 1936, June 14, 1937, October 17, 1937, December 19, 1937, April 3, 1938, June 13, 1938, October 28, 1938, December 13, 1938, February 13, 1939, April, 24, 1945, October 26, 1945, January 3, 1946, May 23, 1946, September 18, 1946, October 7, 1946, November 10, 1948, September 20, 1950, November 3, 1950, December 17, 1952, August 3, 1964
Arnold, Henri of the Salon des Tuileries: May 7, 1929, June 11, 1931
Bachich (?), Oscar: undated letters (2), September 14, 1935, October 29, 1935
Baldenweck: April 16, 1946
Banillot, Ch.: undated letter (1)
Basler, Adolphe: April 20, 1919, April 25, 1929, January 29, 1931
Beaulieu: January 8, 1929*
Benedictus, J.: October 13, 1919*, December 6, 1919*, June 26, 1920*, August 15, 1920*, September 10, 1920*, November 12, 1920*, 1928*
Benoit, M.: May 2, 1944
Berger, Prof.: December 15, 1942, March 29, 1943
Berin (?), Henri: February 1, 1923
Bernard, Jean: undated letter (1), May 21, 1934, November 28, 1936
Berthier, Georges: August 18, 1942, August 26, 1942
Betts, P. C. of the State Department: October 29, 1938
Binon, Denyse: June 30, 1939, August 21, 1945
Binion, Subry: undated* (1), September 13, 1914*, 1939*
Boaq (?), R. M.: January 19, 1927*
Bodtsler, Maria: undated letter (1)
Boll, Marcel: undated letter (1), April 26, 1914, February 21, 1944, March 31, 1944
Bouche, G. Louis (for John Wanamaker): June 23, 1923, September 6, 1923, October 11, 1923, May 12, 24, 1924, July 18, 1924, August 15, 1924, September 27, 1924, October 10, 1924, October 13, 1924
Bouche, G. Louis: May 20, 1926, June 21, 1926
Briotet, Francis: undated letter (1)
Brooker, K. M. (for Forest Monroe): July 30, 1932
Bryant, Harriet of the Carroll Art Galleries: undated letters (4)
Callahan, Miriam: undated letter (1)
Capoll: January 21, 1925
Carco (?): April 20, 1919, April 13, 1921
Carlock, George: undated letters (2), 1916 (31)
Chapin, L.: June 1920*
Chauvin, Madeleine: undated letters (1)
Cheute, Renee (?): undated letter (1)
Choguard, Veuve: February 20, 1923*, June 1928
Clauser, Henry (?): undated letter (1)
Clemenm?, undated letter (1)
Clerge, Auguste: 1927*, February 10, 1927*
Coevoet-Hacart, Andre: October 17, 1945
Compagnie Franco-Suisse: April 15, 1920
Consulat de Suisse, Dijon: May 23, 1942, June 30, 1942, July 20, 1942, July 31, 1944, November 7, 1944
Consulat de Suisse, Paris: July 6, 1942
Coquist, Gustave: undated letter (1)
Cossonet Freres: October 19, 1936
Cottereau, H. of Galerie Choiseul: February 2, 1923
Credit Lyonnais: November 13, 1936
Crofutt (?), Edward F.: undated letter (1), May 1, 1928, September 1929
Danz, Louis: March 5, 1932
Davis, B. of the La France Textile Industries: August 26, 1929
De Gratiollet, Baron d'Aubas: November 26, 1927, December 3, 11, 1927, August 16, 1920
De Ridder, Elisabeth: February 28, 1935, June 16, 1936, January 5, 1937*, March 1, 1939
Depierris, Louise Charlotte: November 22, 1929
De Wrobleroska, L.: September 29, 1924*
Dracopoli, John: December 25, 1921, November 3, 1925, January 10, 1928
Dracopoli, K. N.: undated letters (4), September 7, 1918, March 30, 1921, January 24, 1928
Draft, M. R.: September 13, 1923
Eans (?), Howard J.: May 10, 1919
Editions Salabert: September 26, 1941
Ente Nazionale per le Industrie Turistiche: November 24, 1933
Evans, Aimee: undated letters (11), March 25, 1937, December 14, 1938
Evans, Anne: undated letters (4), May 27, 1929, November 27, 1929, March 9, 1930, August 6, 12, 1930, October 23, 1930, July 3, 1936, December 2, 12, 1936
Evans, John (letter from Russell): November 18, 1944
Eversole, Mary: undated letter (1)
F., Jeanne: December 27, 1931
Flanagan, John: undated letter (1)
Fonbonne, J.: undated letters (2), July 27, 1915, December 11, 1944
Fonten ? R.: June 14, 1934, July 19, 1934, May 6, 1935
Fozet, Jean C.: April 15, 1937*
Fried, Rose (to Simone): May 14, 1954
Frun ?, Yvonne: 1941, September 8, 1942, February 17, 1943
Galerie Danthon: May 8, 1930
Galerie Armand Drouant: November 20, 1926
Gance, Abel: June 10, 1925, December 15, 1925
Gans, Howard S: February 27, 1917, March 17, 1945
Garnsey, Julian Ellsworth: undated letter (1)
Gautherin, Auguste: undated letters (7), July 28, 1923*, July 25, 1924*, July 15, 1926*, November 20, 1926, July 14, 1929*, September 8, 1940
Gavronsky, L.: March 25, 1930, May 3, 1930
Genauer, George: undated letter (1)
Georges, B.: July 26, 1930
Gilboughy (?): February 6, 1911* (2)
Goodwin, Elizabeth Page: undated letter (1)
Hacart, Yves: undated letters (3), March 20, 1939, April 13, 22, 1939, June 20, 1939, August 14, 1939, July 8, 1941, November 14, 1941, May 28, 1942, March 27, 1945
Halo, Leo Greenlaw: March 12, 1945, August 13, 1945
Halperin, Th.: April 8, 12, 23, 1929, February 11, 1930
Halpert, Edith, of Downtown Gallery: September 20, 1929
Hancock (?), Vivi: August 30, 1933
Hirsch, Sidney: undated letters (3)
Howe, Thomas C., Jr.: December 8, 1931
Huston, John: undated letter (1)
Huston, Walter: June 7, 1934 (signed by secretary A. E. Sunderland), October 11, 1934 (signed by Huston)
Imprimerie Studium: December 23, 1926
Iris Letter-box: June 6, 1935
Jonquieres, Henri: July 15, 1926
Jossier, G.: August 5, 1935
Kahn, Gustave: undated letter (1)
Kelly, G: June 29, 1935
Kennicott, Robert Helm: undated letters (6), June 10, 1938, October 1, 1938, August 25, 1939
Kent, Atwater: April 6, 1946, December 7, 1946
Kritchevsky, B.: February 1, 1923
Krohg, Lucy: November 26, 1935, October 7, 31, 1936
L., Jean: July 23, 1910*
La Revue Moderne: June 13, 1923
Landowski, Francoise: September 9, 1937*, December 6, 1938
Lasky, Bessie: undated letter (1)
Le Gaillard: October 15, 20, 1938
Lemoine, Jean Gabriel: undated letters (2), October 21, 1920*, June 3, 1930
Lerondelle, R.: September 30, 1934, January 14, 1936, May 17, 1936, July 13, 1936, July 27, 1937, February 27, 1939*, January 31, 1947, September 18, 1936
Letellier, Pierre: January 7, 1936*
Letty, Junia: undated* (4), October 21, 1923*, 1924*, September 29, 1924*
Lezaner (?), Daniel: October 17, 1927
Liger, Cecil: July 24, 1914*
Lun, Kuen: undated letters (3)
Macay (?): August 15, 1942
Macdonald-Wright, Stanton (to Suzanne): (letters are grouped together after 1964) undated letters (5), May 30, 1953, May 20, 1955, June 22, 1956, June 30, 1956, July 6, 1956, March 5, 1957, August 7, 1957, February 10, 1958, May 13, 1958, November 5, 1959
Madge, E.: June 6, 1935
Madoz, Gastone: August 15, 1935*
Magneron, Jacques: February 12, 1944
Marseille, Leon: May 16, 1918
Mary Pickford Studios: January 5, 1932
Meurer, Giselda: December 12, 1932
Militarverwaltungarat: August 11, 1943, July 6, 1944
Milliers, The: December 1931
Montross, N. E.: September 14, 1917
Morier, M.: undated letter (1)
Mttron-Hirsch, Sidney: May 22, 1923, April 1925
O'Brien, P. P.: August 28, 1931
O'Connor, Sally: March 19, 1931
Osterkamp, F. E.: June 18, 1928, December 2, 1929
Pisar, Charles J. of the American Consular Service: January 5, 1935
Prefecture de l'Yonne: March 7, 1933, March 16, 1933, December 11, 1941, May 21, 1942, September 12, 1942, July 20, 1944
Presses Universitaires de France: April 14, 1944
Preston, Stuart: undated letter (1)
Price, Miriam: undated letter (1)
Public Buildings Administration: May 20, 1940
R., M. V., Feldkommandatur: November 26, 1943
R., Willy S.: undated letter (1), November 20, 1920
Renault, Germaine: January 3, 1925*
Rich, John Hubbard: October 27, 1931
Rider, Ione Morrison: undated letters (2)
Robinson, Alexandre: March 11, 1918, October 13, 1926
Rollins, Lloyd Lapage: November 14, 1931
Rosieres, G.: undated letter (1)
Runyon, Cornelia M.: December 10, 1938
Russell, Morgan to (?): April 18, 1913*, June 6, 1924
Russell's father: December 7, 1909
Ry, Rene: January 8, 1923
S., E. A.: undated letter (1)
S., Michel: July 19, 1935
Sakey: 1945
Sarfatti: January 13, 1937
Sazalgette, L (?): undated letter (1), undated* (1), August 26, 1919, November 2, 1920
Scaifoglio, V.: February 11, 1935
Schanhaft, Petra: July 28, 1931
Sconhoft, E.: November 20, 1930
Scott, Mrs. F. A.: undated letter (1)
Serstevens, O (?): undated letter (1), undated* (1), 191?, September 19, 1919*, October 4, 1920
Severe, Marc. L., of the State Department: August 24, 1932, October 20, 1937, October 25, 1939, February 3, 1940
Societe des Artistes Independants: November 23, 1928
Sol, Louis: undated letters (7), undated* (1), July 18, 1927, November 27, 1929, November 26, 1945?, April 9, 1931, August 12, 1935, November 9, 1943, June 23, 1929
Som_liot (?), T.: undated letter (1)
Sogourin, G.: September 30, 1931*
Starr, Alfred: February 14, 21, 1924
Stravinsky, Igor: February 2, 1916
Studer, Ch.: 1924
T., Hector: December 23, 1931
Taylor, Robert M., the American Consul: February 21, 1946
Telkamp, Gerard: January 1931
Terouelle, J.: undated* {1)
Terullaz (?), H.: undated letter (1)
Turnbull, Blanche: August 13, 1930, September 25, 1930, September 10, 1931, October 17, 1931, March 1, 1932
Turnbull, Ruth: undated letters (6), June 25, 1931, March 5, 1934, August 7, 1934, December 17, 1937, October 4, 1939
U. S. Embassy: May 14, 1940, January 27, 1945
Upton, Louise: December 24, 1931
Vatican City: February 21, 1934
Vauxcelle, L.: June 14, 1919
Viaud-Bruant: undated letters (5), January 3, 31, 1922, February 1, 9, 1922, March 12, 1922, July 6, 1922, January 20, 1923, June 30, 1926, October 7, 1926, November 5, 1926, June 29, 1927
Violette, Jacques: undated letter (1), February 3, 1923
Watson, J., of Art in Federal Buildings: October 23, 1936
Weil, B.: September 18, 1922
Wells (?): July 31, 1932
Whitney, Gertrude Vanderbilt: undated letter (1), December 1, 1913
Wood, John R.: May 9, 1941
Wyler, Melanie: July 16, 1932
Zamie (?): undated letter (1), 1925*, September 12, 1929, January 1930*
Zarraga, A.: undated letter (1)
Zelegua, H.: undated* (1)
Alison (?): May 30, 1921
Augusta: undated letters (3), August 31, 1928, November 26, 1928, December 1929, September 14, 1933
Billy: undated letter (1)
Charles: undated*, May 22, 1910*
Clairette: August 13, 1933*
Dodo: undated letter (1), July 9, 1936
Dorette: November 23, 1935, August 18, 1937*, April 14, 1938*
Fran: March 20, 22, 1946
Fred: undated letters (5), November 25, 1933, December 4, 1933, January 9, 1936, October 13, 1936
Genevieve: October 13, 1914
John, of Universal Pictures Corp.: April 21, 1932
Leo: February 5, 1939
Lucette: undated letters (2), 1913*, August 7, 1913*, October 20, 1913*, March 21, 1914*, June 10, 1920*, February 21, 1926*, September 12, 1932*, September 6, 1933*, August 14, 1935*, August 22, 1935*, September 7, 1924
Lucienne: December 24*, 29*
Lula: May 25, 1910*
Marguerite: July 12, 1910*, July 18, 1913*, May 26, 1932*
Michel: undated letter (1)
Odette: May 25, 1939*
Renee: June 5, 1912*
Robby: undated letters (2), April 1923*, April 25* 1923, October 10, 1923*, October 22, 1925*, May 24, 1929, May 30, 1929, September 12, 1929, November 22, 1929, December 7, 12, 1929, May 5, 1930, July 2, 1930, November 7, 1929
Simone: undated letter (1), 1938*, plus letter from Russell dated June 12, 1945
Simonetta: November 13, 1938*
Suzanne: August 19, 1928*, October 3, 1939
Yvette: September 17, 1945*
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Alvarez, Mabel, 1891-1985; Henri, Robert, 1865-1929; Huston, Walter, 1884-1950; Kikoïne, Michel, 1892-1968; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; Stein, Leo, 1872-1947; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971; Whitney, Gertrude Vanderbilt, 1875-1942
Subjects-Topical:
Synchromism (Art); Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews
Provenance
The Morgan Russell papers were lent to the Archives of American Art for microfilming by the Montclair Art Museum in 1991. The material was returned to the lender in 1992.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Location of Originals
The Morgan Russell papers are owned by the Montclair Art Museum, New Jersey.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35mm microfilm reels 4524-4542 available for use at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1909-1964, Series 1:; (Reels 4524-4527)
  This series contains letters from many prominent individuals who played a significant role in Russell's artistic development, including Mabel Alvarez, Robert Henri, Walter Huston, Michel Kikoine, Stanton Macdonald-Wright, Leo Stein, Igor Stravinsky, and Getrude Vanderbilt Whitney.
  The series begins with correspondence with named correspondents. Named files are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. This is followed by miscellaneous correspondence, arranged chronologically. A list of correspondents included in Miscellaneous Correspondence can be found in Appendix: Miscellaneous Correspondents/Postcards from Series 1.
  Postcards have generally been separated from the miscellaneous correspondence and filmed separately in order to maintain the lender's arrangement, although some postcards are interfiled with the named and miscellaneous correspondence. These are indicated by an asterisk.
  - Apollinaire, Guillame, January 29, 1910, September 20, 1913 (Reel 4524, Frame 3-8)
  - Binion Family: Letters to Georges Binion from Mme. Binion chez Mme. Ratier, September 9, 10, 12, 20*, 20, 22, 23, 25*, 25, 26, 27, 28, 30, 1914, October 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 9 (3 letters), 12, 14, 16, 18, 19 (2 letters), 21, 1914 (Reel 4524, Frame 9-270)
    (includes letters to Denyse Binion: February 14, 1938, March 2, 1938, July 2, 1938 and a letter to Subry Binion from Prof. Berber, October 3, 1940)
  - Cendrars, Blaise, undated (25 letters), February 12, 1918*, January 11, 12, 1920, February 24, 26, 1920, April 9, 1920*, May 14, 1920, January 10, 1925, July 9*, 29, 1926, August 13, 1926*, December 4, 1926* (Reel 4524, Frame 271-343)
  - Conlon, Barnett D., undated (45 letters), August 10, 16, 22, 25, 1916, January 22, 1917, February 20, 1917, March 23, 1917, July 3, 1917, August 5, 1917, May 1, 22, 1918, April 20, 1920, July 22, 1920, February 5, 1921, July 19, 1921 (Reel 4524, Frame 344-572)
  - Head, R. Chalfonte, undated (20 letters), July 12, 1928, December 28, 1928, August 27, 1929, March 20, 1930 (Reel 4524, Frame 573-722)
  - Henri, Robert, May 2, 1910, June 21, 1925, March 6, 1926 (Reel 4524, Frame 723-735)
  - Kikoine, Michel, undated (8 letters), October 13, 1923*, April 10*, 16, 1929, December 23, 1929 (Reel 4524, Frame 736-775)
    (includes a 1925 exhibition catalog)
  - Lee, Arthur, undated (1 letter), August 1913, August 6, 1914 (Reel 4524, Frame 776-800)
  - Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, undated, 1916 (Reel 4524, Frame 801-813)
    (1 undated letter fragment, plus one letter to Russell from Willard Huntington Wright concerning Stanton Macdonald-Wright)
  - Rider, Charles Joseph, undated (1 letter), November 11, 1929, December 5, 22, 1929, January 24, 1930, February 14, 1930, May 19, 1930, June 4, 1930, July 13, 1930, November 28, 1930, March 17, 1931, April 27, 1931, August 8, 1931*, September 2, 1932 (Reel 4524, Frame 814-866)
  - Russell, Morgan (Reel 4524, Frame 867-888)
    (miscellaneous drafts of letters: 3 undated letters, January 12, 1922, February 13, 1943; letter to Francois Mauriac, September 16, 1936)
  - Shore, Viola Brothers, undated (27 letters), February 27, 1930, April 25, 1931, June 30, 1936, February 2, 1937, March 3, 1937, August 19, 1937, January 16, 1938, March 8, 1938 (Reel 4524, Frame 889-1027)
  - Shore, Viola Brothers (letters from Russell), undated (3 letters), February 14, 1937, October 15, 1937*, March 21, 1938, July 13, 14, 1938, September 17, 1938, October 13, 1938, December 13, 16, 1938, January 2, 1939, March 6, 1939, April 14, 1947, July 11, 1947 (Reel 4524, Frame 889-1027)
  - Shore, Wilma, undated (14 letters), July 9, 1930*, June 5, 1931, June 9, 1935, (includes photographs) (Reel 4524, Frame 1028-1081)
  - Stein, Leo, undated (14 letters), July 9, 1910, December 11, 1911, October 7, 1923, November 9, 1928, May 17, 1934, July 10, 1945 (Reel 4525, Frame 3-75)
    (includes 3 undated letters to Stein from Russell)
  - Stein, Nina (wife of Leo Stein), undated (14 letters), August 8, 16, 28, 1920, August 28, 1920, 1923, November 4, 1928, December 18, 1928, June 7, 1929, February 16, 1935, June 30, 1935, July 10, 1940, December 26, 1940 (Reel 4525, Frame 76-158)
  - Suzanne, circa 1936-1937, (46 letters) (Reel 4525, Frame 159-429)
  - Whitney, Gertrude Vanderbilt (Reel 4525, Frame 430-436)
    (September 19, 1915, January 7, 1916 signed by Whitney's secretary, plus a draft of an undated letter to Whitney from Russell)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1909-1936 (Reel 4525, Frame 437-1162)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1937-1959 (Reel 4526, Frame 1-450)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated (Reel 4526, Frame 451-951)
  - Correspondence, Postcards, 1910-1945 (Reel 4527, Frame 1-391)
- Biographical Material, 1925-1941, Series 2:; (Reel 4527)
  This series includes address books, a passport, a French driver's license, art society membership cards and museum entry cards. The material primarily reflects Russell's activities in Europe.
  - Biographical Material, 1925-1941 (Reel 4527, Frame 392-612)
    2 address books, undated
    Passport, 1933-1935
    French museum entry cards, undated and 1926
    Italian museum entry cards, 1934-1935
    50 centavos Paraguaian coin on a ring
    French driver's license, 1925
    2 tickets to Le Salon des Tuileries, 1929-1930
    2 membership cards for the Societe des Artistes Independants, 1939-1941
- Business Records, 1911-1946, Series 3:; (Reel 4527)
  This series consists of receipts and invoices for art supplies, musical and mechanical instruments, and medical services.
  - Receipts and Invoices, 1911-1946 (Reel 4527, Frame 613-830)
- Writings, 1931-1953, Series 4:; (Reel 4527)
  This series consist of transcripts of lectures given by Russell and two essays written about him.
  - Writings (Reel 4527, Frame 831-972)
    "Pastwards" by Russell, 1931
    The first talk given by Russell to the Art Students League, Los Angeles, California, July 16, 1931
    Conference given by Russell at the Museum of the Palace of the Legion of Honor of San Francisco, November 6, 1931, and at the California Art Club, Los Angeles, California, January 1932
    Lecture given by Russell at Stendahl Art Galleries, Los Angeles, California, January 16, 1932
    "Ancient and Renaissance Rome: Impressions of a Painter," December 1935
    "Sur Deux; Tableaux dans la 'Casa Buonarotti a Florence'," 1935-1936
    2 essays about Russell, 1953
- Notes and Sketches, 1891-1977, Series 5:; (Reels 4528-4538)
  The unbound notes and sketches and illustrated notebooks found here contain information concerning color theory, music, and synchromism. Included is a sketch of Stravinsky.
  - Unbound Notes and Sketches, 1891-1977 (Reel 4528)
    - Notes on Color Theory (Reel 4528, Frame 3-56)
    - Notes on Music (Reel 4528, Frame 57-1074)
    - Notes on Music (Reel 4529, Frame 1-152)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4529, Frame 153-1282)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4530, Frame 1-1201)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4531, Frame 1-1257)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4532, Frame 1-1209)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4533, Frame 1-1025)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Sketches (Reel 4534, Frame 1-750)
  - Notebooks, 1909-1939 (Reel 4534, Frame 751-1349)
  - Notebooks, 1909-1939 (Reel 4535, Frame 1-658)
  - Notebooks, 1909-1939 (Reel 4536, Frame 1-1117)
  - Notebooks, 1909-1939 (Reel 4537, Frame 1-818)